Finding aid for the The Ohio State University Health Sciences Library Records
Medical Heritage Center
The Ohio State University Health Sciences Library Records
1933-2013
Medical Heritage Center
The Ohio State University Health Sciences Library
29.25 linear feet
Materials about The Ohio State University Health Sciences Library.
Spec.199902.HSL
History of Organization
The Ohio State University Health Sciences Library evolved from a small collection of books in 1846. The following timeline details the growth and development of this collection and library building. 1846: In the spring of 1846, the Willoughby Medical College near Cleveland, Ohio transferred to Columbus. A few books transferred with the school. These materials, bearing their original bookplates, are currently housed in the Coleman Memorial Alcove on the 5th floor. 1847-1914: The book collection continued to grow with the medical school. Willoughby Medical College undergoes a series of mergers with different names: Starling Medical College (1874-1907), Ohio Medical University (1892-1907), and Columbus Medical College (1876-1892), and Starling-Ohio Medical College (1917-1914). 1914: Starling-Ohio Medical College becomes The Ohio State University College of Medicine. At the same time, a College of Homeopathic Medicine was established through a merger with the Cleveland-Pulte Medical College. 1922: The College of Homeopathic Medicine closed and their collection of over 1,800 volumes became part of the Library collection. Eventually housed at University Library, this homeopathy collection was moved to remote storage in 1992. 1925: The Medical Reference Library (later called the Health Center Library) moved into 1,188 sq. ft. on the first floor of Hamilton Hall. Space for storing less-frequently used material was acquired in the Main Library, its Annex, a basement room in Hamilton Hall, and the headquarter building of The Ohio Tuberculosis Association at 1575 Neil Avenue. The use of library materials was maintained by a messenger service. 1934: The Library maintained 18,500 monographic volumes and subscribed to 164 journal titles in the fields of medicine, dentistry, nursing, and optometry. 1947: The Albert D. Frost Collection in the Department of Ophthalmology came under the direction of the Health Center Library. 1951: Construction of an addition to Hamilton Hall allowed the scattered collection to be returned to one building. Floor space was increased to 6,890 sq. ft. 1954: The library at Children's Hospital came under the direction of the Health Center Library. 1955-1957: The Lionel Topaz Memorial Library in the School of Optometry and the medical reading room of University Hospital came under the direction of the Health Center Library. 1959: Holdings were enhanced by the donation to the University of approximately 8,000 medical and 4,000 dental books and periodicals by the Columbus Public Library. These volumes had been deposited in the Public Library by the Columbus Academy of Medicine, the Ohio State Dental Association, and the Columbus Dental Society. By this date the Library consisted of 67,000 monographic volumes and subscribed to 1,460 journal titles. 1960s: Believing that Library facilities in Hamilton Hall were totally inadequate for the needs of the Library and medical complex, Dr. Richard L. Meiling, Dean of the College of Medicine, instigated a search for funding a new library facility. A grant was obtained through the National Institutes of Health. A stipulation for funding required that innovative technology be included in the construction of the building. Dr. Meiling, Hugh Atkinson, Director of University Libraries, and Mr. Curtis, architect, decided to invest $800,000 in an automated book storage system called the Randtriever (named after the company which developed it). 1972: The new Health Sciences Library, at 376 West 10th Avenue, was completed at a cost of $5 million and was designed to accommodate 1,250 users. Most of the collection, 120,000 volumes, was placed in random order in the Randtriever. 1973: As it was apparent that the Randtriever could not handle the mechanical stress of retrieving items, heavily used materials were pulled out of the Randtriever. Books were placed on the third floor and journals were placed on the second floor. 1987: Due to cost increases and difficulty in maintaining a current optometry collection, the Topaz collection merged with the Health Sciences Library. Although several reference books were left in Fry Hall at the request of faculty to maintain a reading room collection, approximately 4,000 volumes were moved to the Health Sciences Library. 1988: The library building was dedicated the John A. Prior Health Sciences Library on November 1, 1988. Dr. Prior, a respected colleague and teacher, had chaired the committee responsible for coordinating the construction of the Library in the 1970's. 1991: Maintenance costs for maintaining the Randtriever became prohibitive and equipment failure was extremely high. Library staff began to evaluate methods to empty the Randtriever and house the collection. 1992: On August 1, 1992 the outside maintenance contract for the Randtriever was discontinued and on August 23, 1992 the Randtriever shut down. In the following months the collection was manually removed from the Randtriever, sorted by call number order, and transferred to remote storage on Goodale Avenue or placed on new shelving in the Library. The very last book removed from the Randtriever was Orthoptics: A Discussion of Binocular Anomalies. Approximately 103,000 volumes were sent to Goodale during this project. A courier began providing daily delivery of materials to and from this remote facility. The Library’s total collection consisted of approximately 200,000 volumes, with approximately 2,000 journal titles. 1993: Funding is approved for the Library renovation which is scheduled to be finished in the Fall of 1996. Work to be done includes removing the Randtriever, utilizing the first floor, expanding computer resources, adding greater shelving space for collections, and further developing the Library's Medical Heritage Center. 1995: The Jesse Owens Recreation Center South, 175 West 11th Avenue, is transformed into temporary housing for Library collections, staff, and services while the Prior Library is renovated. Journal volumes dated prior to 1960 and books published prior to 1970 were shipped from the Goodale storage facility to the new Book Depository on Kenny Road. 1995: The Health Sciences Library reopened in the Fall of 1995. Several ceremonies took place in late 1995 and early 1996 to recognize the improvements made to the Library. The number of volumes in the collection at this time was approximately 140,000. More recently, library content began to shift from the physical to the virtual. Space being a critical commodity in the Medical Center, the focus of the Prior began to change and include shared education and collaborative space. This transition has included many construction projects to the building and they are outlined below: 2003: the Clinical Skills Education and Assessment Center was built in the basement 2003: offices were constructed on the fourth floor to house the Center for Knowledge Management 2003: the entire first floor was redesigned to create the ASK Desk, pager pick-up booth, DIY workstations, and new mobile friendly furniture 2004-2005: the Health Sciences Copyright Management Office (CMO) was built 2006: room 400A&B was renovated and became a classroom of the future February 16, 2009: a coffee shop, The Caffeine Element, opened on the first floor 2009: the Copyright Management Office moved to newly built space on the second floor and the original CMO office space on the first floor became the Health Sciences Center for Global Health 2009: the Center for Clinical and Translational Science on the second floor was completed 2010-2012: construction of two new floors as part of the College of Medicine Academic Expansion 2010: an ICU simulation suite was added on the second floor 2011: Center for Knowledge Management absorbed into the Health Sciences Library 2011: desk on the first floor gets remodeled with a new collaborative space added behind it November 2011: Building is renamed by Board of Trustees from the John A. Prior Health Sciences Library to John A. Prior Hall and the library organization becomes known as the Health Sciences Library. 2012: Clinical Skills Education and Assessment Center expansion on the 6th floor of Prior Hall opens and the seventh floor is occupied by three departments from the College of Medicine.
Scope and Content
The Ohio State University Health Sciences Library Records (approximately 29.25 linear feet) is material about the organization and physical building of the Health Sciences Library at The Ohio State University. Major highlights of this collection include the randtriever and construction of the Prior Hall building over the course of its lifetime.
Statement of Arrangement
Series I: Oversized (4 boxes) contains one box of construction and renovation blueprints from 1969-1995. There are also two Randtriever bins. The last box of the series contains posters showing the various construction and renovation materials used during the 1996 renovation. These posters show the styles of furniture, carpet and countertops that were chosen for study spaces, workspaces and administrative offices. This series is arranged by item. Series II: Collections (6 boxes) consists of files and newsletters that relate to the books and information available through the Health Sciences Library. This is mostly found through a large amount of administrative statistics that reference aspects such as circulation, digital databases and even statistics from other national health sciences libraries. Also included in this series are other various administrative documents that reference books and collections. This can include information on budgets, correspondence and general reports, as it relates to the library’s collections. This series is arranged alphabetically. In this series there are a variety of acronyms, including: AAHSL: Association of Academic Health Sciences Libraries AAHSLD: Association of Academic Health Sciences Library Directors AAMC: Association of American Medical Colleges ACRL: Association of College and Research Libraries AHC: Association of Academic Health Centers ARL: Association of Research Libraries COHLC: Central Ohio Hospital Library Consortium COMIN: Central Ohio Medical Information Center JCAHO: Joint Commission on Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations MEDLARS: Medical Literature Analysis and Retrieval System OPHILTP: Ohio Public Health Information Literacy Training Project RIST: Reference and Information Services Team Series III: Construction (7 boxes) holds a wide variety of documents pertaining to the original construction of the Health Sciences Library as well as the renovations that followed. However, the majority of the collection is in relation to the renovations rather than the original construction project from 1969. The three most abundant themes in this series are broken down into: Relocation, Correspondence and Furniture, and once again these are mostly referencing the renovation projects. Most of the remaining documents are related to administrative decisions or files containing reports, budgets or correspondence with specific contractors. This series is arranged alphabetically. Series IV: History (4 boxes) contains the general documents and newsletters that reference important milestones and events at the Health Sciences Library. This series is arranged alphabetically. Series V: Media (6 boxes) contains boxes of photos and slides that mostly deal with the renovation and construction projects, but there are also staff and building photos as well. One box of this series houses digital media such as CD’s, floppy disks and DVD’s. This box also contains VHS recordings of the rededication ceremony. Series VI: Randtriever (2 boxes) is dedicated to the construction, history and overall understanding of the Randtriever. The Randtriever was a two-story automated book retrieval system that was part of the original construction project from the 1960’s. The Randtriever and the building were completed in 1972, but the Randtriever became a cause of concern. The automated system did not perform as intended and by 1992 it had been removed. This series is arranged alphabetically.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open to the public and is available for viewing in the Medical Heritage Center. Materials do not circulate and must be used in the supervised reading room. Restrictions, including copyright, may exist and some materials may be too fragile to photocopy or digitize. The MHC charges for duplication services, which must be performed by staff.
Other Finding Aid
https://hsl.osu.edu/sites/default/files/Spec199902HSL_0.pdf
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Ohio State University, Health Sciences Library
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Series I: Oversized (4 boxes) contains one box of construction and renovation blueprints from 1969-1995. There are also two Randtriever bins. The last box of the series contains posters showing the various construction and renovation materials used during the 1996 renovation. These posters show the styles of furniture, carpet and countertops that were chosen for study spaces, workspaces and administrative offices. This series is arranged by item., 1969-2008
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: C. Curtiss Inscho and Associates. Health Sciences Library. Sheets 2, 6-11, 17, 43-46, S 1-9, May 5, 1969 (Box 1, Piece 1)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Central Business Group, Conceptual Spacesaver Layouts, Sheet 1 of 2 and 2 of 2. DB.92392.A, September 23, 1992 (Box 1, Piece 2)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Acock Associates, Phase II Renovations. A2.1-2.5 (June 7, 1995), All. 2, All. 5 (April 5, 1996), 1995-1996 (Box 1, Piece 3)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Acock Associates, Room 205 Renovations. Project #OSU-080256, August 25, 2008 (Box 1, Piece 4)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL C. Curtiss Inscho and Associates, Master Plan. 12 pages, 1969 (Box 1, Piece 5)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL C. Curtiss Inscho and Associates, Original Blueprints. 58 pages, May 5, 1969 (Box 1, Piece 6)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL C. Curtiss Inscho and Associates. Sheets, many hand colored, November 20, 1969 (Box 1, Piece 7)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Floor Plans, Acock Associates. Floors 1-4, Project #DPU315-93-109, November 23, 1993 (Box 1, Piece 8)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Furniture Schedule, Floor 1-4, January 8, 1996 (Box 1, Piece 9)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Improvements, 1990s renovation. Sheets S1-S3, S5 (Box 1, Piece 10)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Improvements, Acock and Associates. Floors- Basement, 1, 2, 3, 4, 1994 (Box 1, Piece 11)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Improvements, Fifth Floor Plan. Project #315-93-109. Sheets A2.5b, A5.5b, A7.1b, A11.5, A12.7, P5, P6, P7, H11, H12, H13, H15, E15, E16, E17, E19, June 6, 1995 (Box 1, Piece 12)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Improvements, Phase II. DPU 315-93-109. Site and Architectural Drawings, No Date (Box 1, Piece 13)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Improvements, Project #GSA 315-93-109. Phase I - Temporary Relocation. A1-A4, M1-M2, E1-E2, March 15, 1995 (Box 1, Piece 14)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Improvements, Project Number GSA 315-93-109. Phase II- Renovation, May 15, 1995 (Box 1, Piece 15)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Schematic Design Proposal, Sheets 1-10, May 13, 1994 (Box 1, Piece 16)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Stage 2, 5th Floor Renovation Project #315-93-109. H 11-15 (June 7, 1995), E5. 15-17,19 (June 7, 1995), 1995-1996 (Box 1, Piece 17)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: HSL Utility Site Plan, Job #A6622. E1-18, H 13-15, H 1-10, P 1-7, U-1, May 5, 1969 (Box 1, Piece 18)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Library Design Associates. Sheets 1-4, August 23, 1994 (Box 1, Piece 19)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Library Designs. JORCS Floor Plan, January and February 1995 (Box 1, Piece 20)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Proposed Schematic Design of 4/15/1994. Sheets 2-5 (2 Copies), April 15, 1994 (Box 1, Piece 21)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Proposed Schematic Design. Sheets 2-5, Alternative Floor Plan First Floor, March 25, 1994 (Box 1, Piece 22)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Schematic Design Proposal of 4/29/1994. Sheets 2-5, April 29, 1994 (Box 1, Piece 23)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Sheets 1-4, Library Design Associates, August 23, 1995 (Box 1, Piece 24)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Telephone and Data Lines on Schematic Design. Sheets 2-5, June 16, 1994 (Box 1, Piece 25)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Worden Sheets 1,2,3,6,7,16. Order #P96-0023. Shelving and Circulation/Desks Reference, No Date (Box 1, Piece 26)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: The Ohio State University Health Sciences Center/Columbus, Ohio, Perkins & Will (4), No Date (Box 1, Piece 27)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Environmental Character Analysis, Perkins & Will, No Date (Box 1, Piece 28)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Datum Level Relationships, Perkins & Will (2), No Date (Box 1, Piece 29)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Existing Utilities, Perkins & Will (5), No Date (Box 1, Piece 30)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Geological Profiles, Perkins & Will (2), No Date (Box 1, Piece 31)
  - Blueprints and Construction Drawings: Medical Center Buildings Maps, Perkins & Will (15), No Date (Box 1, Piece 32)
  - Red Randtriever Storage Bin, No Date (Box 2, Piece 1)
  - Blue Randtreiver Storage Bin, No Date (Box 3, Piece 1)
  - Banner: Prior Health Sciences Library, The Heartbeat of OSU Health Sciences Center, No Date (Box 4, Piece 1)
  - Holland Meyers Architectural Drawing: HSL, No Date (Box 4, Piece 2)
  - Poster: Administrative Offices; Materials Used for Furniture and Construction, No Date (Box 4, Piece 3)
  - Poster: Call Bell Drawing, 1997 (Box 4, Piece 4)
  - Poster: “The Heraldry of the College of Medicine’s Schools”, No Date (Box 4, Piece 5)
  - Poster: HSL Art and Office Space, No Date (Box 4, Piece 6)
  - Poster: HSL Seal/Emblem Color Comparison, No Date (Box 4, Piece 7)
  - Poster: Scrupulograph Drawing, 1997 (Box 4, Piece 8)
  - Poster: Scrupulograph Drawing, 1997 (Box 4, Piece 9)
  - Poster: Scrupulograph Drawing, 1997 (Box 4, Piece 10)
  - Poster: Staff Work Areas; Materials Used for Furniture and Construction (Poster 1 of 4), No Date (Box 4, Piece 11)
  - Poster: Staff Work Areas; Materials Used for Furniture and Construction (Poster 2 of 4), No Date (Box 4, Piece 12)
  - Poster: Staff Work Areas; Materials Used for Furniture and Construction (Poster 3 of 4), No Date (Box 4, Piece 13)
  - Poster: Staff Work Areas; Materials Used for Furniture and Construction (Poster 4 of 4), No Date (Box 4, Piece 14)
  - Poster: Vision/Double Desk Drawing, 1997 (Box 4, Piece 15)
  - Poster: X-Ray Viewer Drawing, 1997 (Box 4, Piece 16)
- Series II: Collections (6 boxes) consists of files and newsletters that relate to the books and information available through the Health Sciences Library. This is mostly found through a large amount of administrative statistics that reference aspects such as circulation, digital databases and even statistics from other national health sciences libraries. Also included in this series are other various administrative documents that reference books and collections. This can include information on budgets, correspondence and general reports, as it relates to the library’s collections. This series is arranged alphabetically. In this series there are a variety of acronyms, including: AAHSL: Association of Academic Health Sciences Libraries AAHSLD: Association of Academic Health Sciences Library Directors AAMC: Association of American Medical Colleges ACRL: Association of College and Research Libraries AHC: Association of Academic Health Centers ARL: Association of Research Libraries COHLC: Central Ohio Hospital Library Consortium COMIN: Central Ohio Medical Information Center JCAHO: Joint Commission on Accreditation of Healthcare Organizations MEDLARS: Medical Literature Analysis and Retrieval System OPHILTP: Ohio Public Health Information Literacy Training Project RIST: Reference and Information Services Team, 1964-2010
  - AAHSL Editorial Board, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - AAHSL Editorial Board, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - AAHSL Editorial Board, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - AAHSL Editorial Board, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - AAHSL Editorial Board, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - AAHSL Editorial Board, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - AAHSL Membership Directory 2007 and AAHSL/AAHSLD 28th Annual Report 2005-2006, 2005-2007 (Box 5, Folder 6.1)
  - AAHSL Membership Directory 2008 and AAHSL/AAHSLD 29th Annual Report 2006-2007, 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 6.2)
  - AAHSL Membership Directory 2009 and AAHSL/AAHSLD 30th Annual Report 2007-2008, 2007-2009 (Box 5, Folder 6.3)
  - AAHSL Membership Directory 2010 and AAHSL/AAHSLD 31th Annual Report 2008-2009, 2008-2010 (Box 5, Folder 6.4)
  - AASHLD: Reports, Newsletters and Correspondence (File 1 of 2), 1977-1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - AASHLD: Reports, Newsletters and Correspondence (File 2 of 2), 1977-1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - AASHLD: Reports, Newsletters and Correspondence (File 1 of 2), 1983-1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - AASHLD: Reports, Newsletters and Correspondence (File 2 of 2), 1983-1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - AASHLD: Reports, Newsletters and Correspondence, 1992-1997 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - AAHSLD: “Report on Automation Activities of Member Libraries”, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - AAHSLD: Survey (File 1 of 2), 1988 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - AAHSLD: Survey (File 2 of 2), 1988 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - AAMC, 2003-2006 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - AAMC: “Academic Information in the Academic Health Sciences Center”, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - AAMC: Annual Report, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - AAMC: Board of Directors, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - AAMC: Correspondence, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - AAMC: “The Health Sciences Library in the Academic Medical Center”, September 1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - AAMC: Newsletter, “Washington Highlights”, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - AAMC: Preliminary Program, 1983, 1984, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - AAMC: Questionnaire Analysis, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - AAMC: Task Force on the Generalist Physician, Executive Summary, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Academic Library Report, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Acquisition and Bindery, 1992-2006 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Acquisitions Budget, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - ACRL: Conference Program, 1998-2005 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - ACRL: News Leader Orientation, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - ACRL: Volunteer Form, December 4, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - AHC Gateway, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 13)